From jungle to pasture, 25 years
of coverage change in Guerrero using
Terra satellite data.
Between 2001 and 2024, Guerrero
lost approximately
hectares of forest. This study analyzes
where and when that loss occurred and what
means for communities and
ecosystem services.
Our objectives were 3: number one,
quantify the magnitude and distribution
spatial scale of forest loss; number
2, relate the changes in NDVI
as a proxy for plant productivity; and
number 3, identify the hotspots
priority for restoration and
conservation.
We process mission data
The Land of Ways
MCD one 2 Q
one annual coverage
Modus MOD uno 3 Q
one NDVI and Aster,
high quality images
resolution. We carry out
thematic classification, matrices of
change per five-year period, detection of
NDBI anomalies and
visual validation with Aster in
hotspots.
Main results, loss
accumulated in the State was
29,660 hectares.
Atoyac de Ãlvarez concentrated
1567 hectares, the
5.3%. Were observed
peaks in 2014 and
2024. Come in
2016 and 2024. Atoyac
explains 8.4% of the
state loss. 712
570 equals 1282
hectares compared to 15,262
hectares in the State
They detected significant drops in the
NDVI in deforested areas,
which confirms a reduction in the
plant productivity.
Timelapse and mapping show
that deforestation is concentrated
mainly in northern municipalities and
northwest, while the large coast
retains more forest cover. The
pressure is associated with slopes already
areas near roads.
Losses are not random,
are linked to the expansion of livestock farming,
opening of roads and recurrent use of the
fire. The loss of forest
reduces ecosystem services,
water regulation, conservation of
soil and carbon sequestration. The
open satellite monitoring is key
to guide local actions.
We propose community reforestation
in critical basins, management
comprehensive fire management with local brigades,
protection of slopes, terraces and
living barriers, monitoring
participatory with Google Earth Engine
and territorial planning that limits the
expansion of pastures.
Open science plus community action,
path towards the restoration of the
ecosystems. Thank you.